Oscar S. Straus Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Oscar S. Straus Papers 1856-1955 (bulk 1856-1923)
MSS41749
Straus, Oscar S. (Oscar Solomon), 1850-1926
37,000 items
50 containers plus 1 oversize
21 linear feet
1 microfilm reel
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Attorney, businessman, public official, diplomat, United States secretary of commerce and labor, and author. Correspondence, diaries, speeches, writings, legal records, pamphlets, clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, and other papers relating chiefly to Straus's service as minister and later ambassador to the Ottoman Empire (Turkey), United States secretary of commerce and labor, and member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration, Hague, Netherlands.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bacon, Robert, 1860-1919--Correspondence.; Barrett, John, 1866-1938--Correspondence.; Bayard, Thomas F. (Thomas Francis), 1828-1898--Correspondence.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947--Correspondence.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919--Correspondence.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908--Correspondence.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933--Correspondence.; Easley, Ralph M. (Ralph Montgomery), 1858- --Correspondence.; Garfield, James Rudolph, 1865-1950--Correspondence.; Griscom, Lloyd Carpenter, 1872-1959--Correspondence.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923--Correspondence.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901--Correspondence.; Hay, John, 1838-1905--Correspondence.; Kohns, Lee, 1864-1927--Correspondence.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928--Correspondence.; Lavanburg, Louis.; Loeb, William, Jr., 1866-1937--Correspondence.; McKinley, William, 1843-1901--Correspondence.; Ochs, Adolph S. (Adolph Simon), 1858-1935--Correspondence.; Peabody, George Foster, 1852-1938--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Straus, Isidor, 1845-1912--Correspondence.; Straus, Isidor, 1845-1912.; Straus, Nathan, 1848-1931--Correspondence.; Straus, Oscar S. (Oscar Solomon), 1850-1926.; Strauss family.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924--Correspondence.
Organizations
Industrial Conference (1919-1920: Washington, D.C.); League to Enforce Peace (U.S.); National Civic Federation.; New York (State). Public Service Commission.; Oscar S. Straus Memorial Association. Oscar S. Straus Memorial Association records. 1927-1954.; Permanent Court of Arbitration.; United States. Department of Commerce and Labor.
Subjects
Arbitration (International law); Diplomatic and consular service, American--Turkey.; Freedom of religion--Turkey.; Industrial relations--United States.; Labor policy--United States.; Wages--Railroads--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
Egypt--Description and travel.; Romania.; Russia.; Turkey--Foreign relations--United States.; Turkey--History--Ottoman Empire, 1288-1918.; United States--Economic policy.; United States--Foreign relations--Turkey.
Occupations
Authors.; Businessmen.; Cabinet officers.; Diplomats.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Oscar S. Straus, attorney, businessman, public official, diplomat, United States secretary of commerce and labor, and author, were given to the Library of Congress by the Oscar S. Straus Memorial Association, Inc., in 1945-1956.
Transfers
A pamphlet has been transferred to the Rare Book and Special Collections Division where it is identified as part of the Oscar S. Straus Papers.
Additional Guides
An alphabetically arranged index and a chronologically arranged calendar are available in the Manuscript Reading Room. A description of the Oscar S. Straus Papers appeared in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions 7, no.2 (February 1950): 3-6.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Oscar S. Straus are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on one reel. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1850, Dec. 23 Born, Otterberg, Bavaria
1854 Came to America and lived in Talbotton, Ga.
1865 Moved to New York, N.Y.
1871 A.B., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1873 LL.D., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1873 1881 Practiced law, New York, N.Y.
1881 1906 Member of the firm L. Straus & Sons, importers of pottery and glassware
1882 Married Sarah Lavenburg (died 1945)
1885 Published The Origin of Republican Form of Government in the United States of America. New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons
1887 1889 Minister to Ottoman Empire (Turkey)
1894 Published Roger Williams, the Pioneer of Religious Liberty. New York: The Century Co.
1898 1899 Minister to Ottoman Empire (Turkey)
1902 1924 Appointed member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration, Hague, Netherlands
1906 1909 United States secretary of commerce and labor; first Jew appointed to a cabinet position
1909 1910 Ambassador to Ottoman Empire (Turkey)
1912 Chairman, arbitration commission to decide wage dispute between eastern railways and their engineers
1913 Published The American Spirit. New York: The Century Co.
1915 1918 Chairman, New York Public Service Commission, First District
1919 Chairman, Paris Committee of the League to Enforce Peace
1919 1920 Member, President's Second Industrial Conference to establish a code of industrial relations
1922 Published autobiography Under Four Administrations, from Cleveland to Taft; Reflections of Oscar S. Straus. New York: Houghton Mifflin
1926, May 3 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Oscar Solomon Straus (1850-1926) span the years circa 1856-1955, with the bulk of the material dating from 1856 to 1923. The collection chiefly relates to Straus's service as minister and later ambassador to the Ottoman Empire (Turkey), United States secretary of commerce and labor, and member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration, Hague, Netherlands. When appointed by Theodore Roosevelt in 1906 as secretary of commerce and labor, Straus became the first Jew to hold a cabinet post. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Diaries and Notebooks, Scrapbooks, Miscellany, and Addition. A select index of correspondence from Theodore Roosevelt and his secretaries appears at end of the container list.
The Correspondence includes general correspondence and letterbooks of Straus's outgoing letters. In the early correspondnece are letters between Straus and his older brothers, Nathan and Isidor, with many of Isidor's letters written during Straus's first appointment as minister to the Ottoman Empire (Turkey). Other correspondents from Straus's career include Robert Bacon, John Barrett, Thomas F. Bayard, Nicholas Murray Butler, Andrew Carnegie, Grover Cleveland, Calvin Coolidge, Ralph M. Easley, James Rudolph Garfield, Lloyd Carpenter Griscom, Warren G. Harding, Benjamin Harrison, John Hay, Lee Kohns, Robert Lansing, William Loeb, William McKinley, Adolph S. Ochs, George Foster Peabody, Theodore Roosevelt, Elihu Root, William H. Taft, and Woodrow Wilson.
The Diaries and Notebooks series contains diaries covering Straus's career and miscellaneous notebooks. The diaries begin with Straus's first appointment as minister to the Ottoman Empire (Turkey) from 1887 to 1888, resume with his second appointment to that post from 1898 to 1900, then cover the remainder of his career beginning with his appointment as secretary of labor and commerce in 1906 through his appointment as a member of the President's Second Industrial Conference in 1919 and end in 1923. A discrete set of notes tucked inside the 1887-1888 diary is Straus's memorandum about a trip to Egypt in March-April 1888. Also included in the folder with the diary is a memorandum and letter recounting infringements on religious liberty in the empire probably in violation of the Berlin treaty of 1878. The miscellaneous notebooks include lecture notes and thoughts and quotations kept by Straus and two notebooks in shorthand kept by Straus's personal secretary, Theodore Linus Weed.
The Scrapbooks, though arranged somewhat chronologically, are largely topical. Individual scrapbooks cover Straus's publications The Origin of Republican Form of Government in the United States of America; Roger Williams, the Pioneer of Religious Liberty; and The American Spirit. Other volumes include his involvement with the Ottoman Empire (Turkey); the Permanent Court of Arbitration; the National Civic Federation; his years in the cabinet; Romania and Russia; the death of his father-in-law Louis Lavenburg; World War I; and the death of Straus himself. Selected items have been microfilmed.
Miscellany contains manuscripts of Straus's publications and speeches, commemorative items, photographs, clippings and other printed matter, diplomas, and an autobiography of Isidor Straus published posthumously. Included also are the minutes of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace and a memorial address in memory of John Hay.
The Addition is comprised of the records of the Oscar S. Straus Memorial Association. Included is correspondence, congressional resolutions, minutes, clippings, blueprints, and mailing lists covering the public subscription campaign and the construction of a memorial to Straus in Washington, D.C., and a lecture series given under the aegis of the association entitled "Commentary on Pan American Problems" and presented by Ricardo J. Alfaro.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Correspondence, 1856-1931
Diaries and Notebooks, 1871-1923
Scrapbooks, 1885-1926
Miscellany, 1868-1955
Addition, 1927-1954
Container List
- Correspondence, 1856-1931 (Box 1-21)
  Letters sent and received, including photocopies of correspondence from other parts of the collection, along with clippings and other printed matter, drafts of documents, essays, notes, photographs, and speeches.
  Arranged under general correspondence and letterbooks and therein chronologically.
  - General correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1856-1888, (6 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1889-1898, (6 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1899, Jan.-1904, June, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1904, July 6-1906, Nov. 15, (6 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1906, Nov. 16-1907, Feb. 14, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1907 (Box 6)
      - Feb. 15-May 16, (6 folders) (Box 6)
      - May 17-Oct. 15, (8 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1907, Oct. 16-1908, Jan. 31, (7 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1908 (Box 9)
      - Feb. 1-May 15, (7 folders) (Box 9)
      - May 16-Oct. 31, (9 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1908, Nov.-1909, Jan., (6 folders) (Box 11)
    - 1909, Feb. 1-1912, Oct. 20, (9 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1912, Oct. 21-1916, Dec. 27, (9 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1917-1918, (9 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1919-1925, (11 folders) (Box 15)
    - 1926, (12 folders) (Box 16)
    - 1928-1931 (Box 17)
    - Undated (Box 17)
  - Letterbooks (Box 17)
    - 1873-1889, (2 vols.) (Box 17)
    - 1889-1897, (2 vols.) (Box 18)
    - 1898-1903, (3 vols.) (Box 19)
    - 1906-1908, (3 vols.) (Box 20)
    - 1908-1909, (3 vols.) (Box 21)
- Diaries and Notebooks, 1871-1923 (Box 21-24)
  Handwritten and typed diaries, with correspondence, clippings, photographs, and other material laid or pasted in, and miscellaneous notebooks. Correspondence tipped into the volumes has been photocopied and the photocopies inserted chronologically in the Correspondence series.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically. See Select Index of Theodore Roosevelt Correspondence and Related Items
  - Notebooks (Box 21)
    - 1871, college lecture notes on metaphysics (Box 21)
    - 1872, thoughts and quotations (Box 21)
    - 1908, June 21, shorthand notes (Box 21)
    - Undated, stenographer's notebook of Theodore Linus Weed labeled "Weed's Notes, No. 2, Diary" (Box 21)
  - Diaries (Box 22)
    - 1887-1888, 1898-1900, 1906-1907, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1908-1914, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - 1914-1923, (5 folders) (Box 24)
- Scrapbooks, 1885-1926 (Box 25-37)
  Clippings, correspondence, photographs, calling cards, and printed matter. Correspondence tipped into the volumes has been photocopied and the photocopies inserted chronologically in the Correspondence series. Selected items are available on Microfilm shelf no. 8,924.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1885-1886 (Box 25)
  - 1887-1889 (Box 25)
  - 1887-1889 (Box 26)
  - 1894-1897 (Box 26)
  - 1898-1900 (Box 26)
  - 1898-1899 (Box 27)
  - 1901-1902 (Box 27)
  - 1901-1905 (Box 27)
  - 1901 (Box 28)
  - 1901-1904 (Box 28)
  - 1902-1905 (Box 29)
  - 1904 (Box 30)
  - 1906 (Box 30)
  - 1909 (Box 31)
  - 1907-1908 (Box 32)
  - 1908 (Box 32)
  - 1908 (Box 33)
  - 1908 (Box 34)
  - 1908 (Box 35)
  - 1909 (Box 35)
  - 1913 (Box 36)
  - 1918 (Box 36)
  - 1926 (Box 36)
- Miscellany, 1868-1955 (Box 38-OV 43)
  Speeches and writings, clippings, commemorative items, diplomas, memorials, minutes, photographs, printed matter, an autobiography of Isidor Straus, and other miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Commemorative items from dinner given by citizens of New York for Straus, 1909 (Box 38)
  - Memorials on death of Straus, 1926, (6 vols.) (Box 38)
  - Minutes of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1922-1925, (2 vols.) (Box 39)
  - Notes, 1922, undated (Box 39)
  - Speeches and writings by Straus (Box 39)
    - "The Origin of Republican Form of Government in the United States and the Hebrew Commonwealth," speech, 1884 (Box 39)
    - The Origin of Republican Form of Government in the United States of America, draft, circa 1885, (2 folders) (Box 39)
    - Roger Williams, the Pioneer of Religious Liberty, draft, circa 1894, (3 folders) (Box 39)
    - The United States and Russia: Their Historical Relations, 1905 (Box 40)
    - "Address of Hon. Oscar S. Straus, Secretary of Commerce and Labor, at the Banquet to General Kuroki," 1907 (Box 40)
    - Under Four Administrations, from Cleveland to Taft; Reflections of Oscar S. Straus, draft, circa 1922, (2 folders) (Box 40)
  - Autobiography of Isidor Straus, 1955 (Box 40)
  - Printed matter and clippings (Box 40)
    - 1868-1871, 1889-1920, (4 folders) (Box 40)
    - 1921-1925, undated, (2 folders) (Box 41)
  - Photographs, 1888-1889, 1897, 1909, 1915-1923, 1943, undated, (2 folders) (Box 41)
  - Unsorted newspaper clippings, circa 1898-circa 1912, (2 folders) (Box 41)
  - Commemorative book on dedication of Oscar S. Straus Memorial, Washington, D.C., 1947 (Box 42)
  - Diplomas, circa 1871-circa 1873 (Box OV 43)
  - Convocation program, Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1904 (Box OV 43)
  - Photograph of Nathan, Oscar, and Isidor Straus, undated (Box OV 43)
  - Printed memorial address from the Jews of America and Great Britain to Clara Hay, in memory of her deceased husband, John Hay, 1905 (Box OV 43)
- Addition, 1927-1954 (Box 44-51)
  Correspondence, congressional resolutions, minutes, clippings, receipts, blueprints, and mailing lists relating to the Oscar S. Straus Memorial Association.
  Arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  - Oscar S. Straus Memorial Association (Box 44)
    - Correspondence and other papers (Box 44)
      - 1927-1930, (17 folders) (Box 44)
      - 1931-1935, (9 folders) (Box 45)
      - 1936-1938, (12 folders) (Box 46)
      - 1939-1940, (8 folders) (Box 47)
      - 1941-1943, (7 folders) (Box 48)
      - 1944-1946, (8 folders) (Box 49)
      - 1947 (Box 49)
        - Jan.-Sept., (3 folders) (Box 49)
        - Oct.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 50)
      - 1948-1954, (6 folders) (Box 50)
    - Agreement, 1940 (Box 51)
    - Blueprints, circa 1940-circa 1941 (Box 51)
    - Clippings, 1929-1933 (Box 51)
    - Mailing lists, undated (Box 51)
Select Index of Theodore Roosevelt Correspondence and Related Items
Theodore Roosevelt
Typewritten letter from Roosevelt re transfer of George Baldwin of Maryland from confidential clerk to first auditor, Civil Service June 22, 1894
Roosevelt re Miller and trade union Oct. 1, 1903
Roosevelt congratulating Straus (new Republic of Panama) Nov. 12, 1903
Roosevelt re passport question Aug. 5, 1904
Roosevelt re Jews, Catholics, and Protestants Oct. 15, 1904
Roosevelt invitation to Straus to talk things over Nov.11, 1904
Roosevelt with handwritten postscript re ambassador to Russia appointment Dec. 16, 1904
Invitation to lunch Jan. 7, 1905
Roosevelt re Russia-Japan conference June 15, 1905
Roosevelt re Russian Jew question Aug. 16, 1905
Roosevelt re Jewish Russia Dec. 14, 1905
Roosevelt re cabinet appointment of Straus Jan. 13, 1906
Roosevelt with handwritten notations re Germany and Morocco matter Feb. 27, 1906
Handwritten note of Roosevelt re Kent of Virginia No date
Roosevelt re Russian massacres of Jews Apr. 10, 1906
Roosevelt re Russian massacres of Jews Apr. 13, 1906
Roosevelt acknowledging telegram of Straus Sept. 2, 1906
Roosevelt complimenting Straus article about attack upon Jews Sept. 6, 1906
Roosevelt re Hughes campaign and Jewish vote (2 letters) Oct. 9-13, 1906
Roosevelt re appointment Oct. 26, 1906
Roosevelt re Miss Rosa Mordecai Oct. 29, 1906
Letter dictated by Roosevelt signed by William Loeb, Jr., re Mordecai Labor Oct. 31, 1906
Roosevelt re appointment Dec. 6, 1906
Melville Fuller, Chief Justice of U.S., re Nobel Prize Jan. 4, 1907
Roosevelt re shipping matters to Straus as secretary of commerce and labor Jan. 11, 1907
Roosevelt re labor decision in South Carolina Jan. 18, 1907
Roosevelt re Bureau of Labor Feb. 20, 1907
Roosevelt re Sunday work in departments Mar. 25, 1908
Elihu Root re Roosevelt’s direction appointing Straus to Hague Convention Apr. 30, 1908
Roosevelt re estimate of men of Roosevelt’s administration May 23, 1908
Roosevelt re Hughes renomination Aug. 29, 1908
Roosevelt re position to Keefe Sept. 15, 1908
Roosevelt to secretary of commerce and labor asking for information Dec. 22, 1908
Roosevelt with notes re absorption of Tennessee Coal and Iron Company Jan. 29, 1909
Roosevelt from Outlook office re census matters June 30, 1911
Roosevelt thanking Straus for fruit Oct. 19, 1911
Roosevelt re Hearst papers and Woodrow Wilson nomination June 7, 1912
Roosevelt re gubernatorial campaign Sept. 8, 1912
Telegram of Roosevelt re Progressive nomination from Tennessee Sept. 25, 1912
Roosevelt re election in Michigan of Progressive Feb. 24, 1913
Roosevelt general information, also comments re Straus’s candidacy for governor July 11, 1918
Secretaries to Theodore Roosevelt
William Loeb, Jr., re Roosevelt’s thanks for admirable speech of Straus Oct. 23, 1903
William Loeb, Jr., re Roosevelt’s invitation to lunch Oct. 31, 1903
William Loeb, Jr., re International Arbitration Congress Jan. 14, 1904
William Loeb, Jr., re acknowledging letter, etc. Aug. 13, 1904
William Loeb, Jr., re minister to Roumania Nov. 19, 1904
William Loeb, Jr., re invitation of Roosevelt to luncheon Mar. 7, 1905
William Loeb, Jr., re immigration bill June 5, 1906
William Loeb, Jr., re appointment to Hague Tribunal Apr. 29, 1908
Letter of Elihu Root, informing Straus of Roosevelt’s pleasure of reappointment to Hague Tribunal Apr. 29, 1908
Alvey A. Adee, re death of former president Grover Cleveland June 24, 1908
William Loeb, Jr., re invitation to dinner Nov. 4, 1908
Two letters signed by Edith Kermit Roosevelt